Daniel Ballesteros-Chávez

Personal Data

Citizenship: Mexican.

Address: 8 Ninth Avenue. Newcastle Upon Tyne, UK. NE6 5XX.

Phone: +447417427620

email: daniel.ballesteros-chavez@durham.ac.uk
Occupation: PhD Student, Durham University.

Field of study: Geometric Analysis. Differential Geometry. Nonlinear elliptic problems in

Geometry.

Web: ennaniux.github.io

Research Plan

The aim of my research is to study the existence of spacelike hypersurfaces in de Sitter space with prescribed symmetric curvature. We restrict to the case when the hypersurface is the graph of a sphere and we consider the class of corresponding functions for which the equation is also elliptic. We have obtained C^0 and C^1 a priori estimates using barrier conditions and we are currently working on the C^2 estimates by means of curvature bounds. These estimates and the Evans-Krylov theorem for concave elliptic fully nonlinear equations will be sufficient for obtaining solutions via the continuity method.

I am also interested in generalisations of this problem, for instance looking at graphs over compact manifolds with prescribed curvature in product spaces with indefinite metric and also I will like to study the corresponding Dirichlet problems and the boundary conditions that may be suitable for these equations.

Education

September 2019 | Expected Philosophie Doctor Candidate in MATHEMATICS, Durham Univer-

sity. Department of Mathematical Sciences.

Thesis: The prescribed curvature problem in spaces of indefinite signature and

fully nonlinear elliptic problems.

Supervisors: Dr. Wilhelm Klingenberg.

Dr. Ben Lambert

November 2013 | Master of Science in MATHEMATICS, Universidad Nacional Autónoma de

México, UNAM. Instituto de Matemáticas.

General knowledge exams: Differential Geometry, General Topology, (Real and

Complex) Analysis.

Thesis: Minimal immersions of Einstein-Kähler manifolds. (in Spanish).

Supervisor: Dr. Gabriel Ruiz Hernández

February 2011 | Undergraduate degree in Physics and Mathematics, Instituto Politécnico

Nacional, IPN. Escuela Superior de Física y Matemáticas, ESFM.

Thesis: On the foundations of the quaternionic analysis and its relationship

with complex analysis. (in spanish).

Supervisor: Dra. María Elena Luna Elizarrarás.

Articles

• Curvature estimates of spacelike surfaces in de Sitter space.

Daniel Ballesteros-Chávez. arXiv:1905.09587 [math.DG] 2019.

Submitted to Manuscripta Matematica

Scholarships

Jan 2011 - Jul 2012 | CONACYT - Becas Nacionales de Posgrado.

Scholarship offered by the Mexican government to complete a master degree

programme.

Oct 2015 - present | CONACY

CONACYT - Becas al Extranjero.

Scholarship offered by the Mexican government to complete a doctoral degree

programme.

Teaching experience

Teaching assistant , Facultad de Ciencias, UNAN	1:
DIEDERATIAL CROMPERN IN LORENZ MINKOWS	7.T. (

2012-1 | Differential Geometry in Lorenz-Minkowski space

2012-1 | Convex Sets

2012-2 | SEVERAL VARIABLE CALCULUS

Teaching assistant, Durham University:

Epiphany 2016 | Analysis in Many Variables,

Complex Analysis.

Michaelmas 2017 | Analysis I.

Epiphany 2018 | Analysis I.

Talks

May 2012	On the ellipticity of the Laplace operator. Fellow Junior Seminar. IM-UNAM.
Nov 2015	On the Existence of Convex Surfaces with Prescribed k-Symmetric Curvatures. Geometry and Topology Seminar. Durham University.
Feb 2016	Poster. Prescribing Homogeneous Curvatures in Hyperbolic space. Winter School 2016 on Geometric Evolution Equations. Regensburg University.
May 2016	On the Minkowski Problem in Hyperbolic Space. 9th European Conference on Elliptic and Parabolic Problems. Institut Für Mathematik Universität Zürich.
Jul 2016	Poster. Dirichlet Problem for Prescribed Curvature in Hyperbolic Space. LMS-CMI Research School. READING UNIVERSITY.
Apr 2017	Fully nonlinear PDE on the sphere from prescribed curvature problem in hyperbolic space. British Mathematical Colloquium. Durham University.
Mar 2018	Prescribed k-curvature of convex closed hypersurfaces in H^n and S^n : a fully nonlinear elliptic problem. Yorkshire and Durham Geometry Days. Durham University.
Jun 2018	Sobre el problema no lineal de k-curvatura prescrita en hipersuperficies del espacio hiperbólico y de Sitter. Mexican Mathematicians in the World. Casa Matemática Oaxaca.
Aug 2018	Poster. Dirichlet Problem for Prescribed Curvature in Hyperbolic Space (revisited). International Conference of Mathematical Sciences (ICMS). MALTEPE UNIVERISTY, ISTANBUL.

Work Experience

Beside the academic experience, I have also been employed as a professional mathematician. In the National Statistical Institute of México, INEGI, the projects I was mainly involved are the national crime survey EN-VIPE, urban public security ENSU and the quality of public services ENCIG. The duties and responsibilities I had included the sampling design, field work supervision and data analysis of multi-stage probabilistic surveys in households to obtain information about common crime. This experience also granted me with the sufficient skills to cooperate in international projects coordinated by the United Nations Office on Drugs and Crime UNODC,

such as the firsts national surveys to measure common crime in both Panamá and Guatemala.

Oct 2016 - Feb 2017	Individual consultant. Analyst of Crime Surveys. United Nations Office on
	Drugs and Crime, UNODC.
Apr 2015 - Aug 2015	Deputy Director of Modelling. National Statistical Institute, INEGI.
$\operatorname{Mar} 2013$ - $\operatorname{Mar} 2015$	Head of Department of Modelling. National Statistical Institute, INEGI.
May 2012 - Feb 2013	Head of the Department of SURVEYS. National Statistical Institute, INEGI.

Other Info

- Seminar organiser: Graduate students seminar in Durham University form Oct. 2017.
- Languages: Spanish (native); English (fluent); Polish (beginner).
- Software and Programming: Linux Debian (advanced); R (advanced); libreOffice and MS Office (advanced); sql (intermediate); lisp (intermediate).

References

Dr. Wilhelm Klingenberg.

Address: Department of Mathematical Science. Durham University.

Phone: +44 (0) 191 334 3069

email: wilhelm.klingenberg@durham.ac.uk

Dr. Ben Lambert.

Address: Department of Mathematics. University College London.

email: b.lambert@ucl.ac.uk

Dr. Gabriel Ruiz-Hernández.

Address: IMATE-UNAM, Ciudad Universitaria, Ciudad de México.

Phone: +52 (55) 5622 4748, ext: 24748.

email: gruiz@matem.unam.mx